Boker tov בוקר
טוב Boker tov to pick up today's daf דף daf Samech-Tet ס"ט
Samech-Tet 69. We're in the middle of Samech-Chet Amud Bet ס"ח עמוד
ב Samech-Chet Amud Bet and we're in the middle of a obviously
extremely important discussion because it is the last point of the mishnah
משנה mishnah which is that the child of a shifchah שפחה shifchah
of a slave woman is a slave and the Gemara גמרא Gemara
learns that from the pasuk פסוק pasuk Ha'isha veyeladeha tihyeh leadoneha האשה
וילדיה תהיה לאדוניה Ha'isha veyeladeha tihyeh leadoneha
that even if you had a non-slave man had children with this
slave woman that the children are still slaves and then that's not
so nogaya נוגע nogaya for us and then the halacha הלכה halacha
that the child of a non-Jewish woman and a Jewish man is
not Jewish. The mishnah משנה mishnah doesn't explicitly say the reverse that
a Jewish mother and a non-Jewish man is Jewish but anyway this
is the Gemara גמרא Gemara about matrilineal descent and the Gemara גמרא
Gemara says how that we know that because the pasuk פסוק pasuk
says
you know what I'm just going to read this I know you
did this yesterday but I just need to reread this. So we're
going to pick up from actually the top it's better so we'll
pick up from the top of Samech-Chet Amud Bet ס"ח עמוד ב.
Samech-Chet Amud Bet. The Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this: Nochrit minalan
נוכרית מנלן? Nochrit minalan? Two lines from the top. How do you
know by a non-Jewish woman that the child is not Jewish? Amar
kra אמר קרא: Amar kra: Lo titchaten bam לא תתחתן בם, Lo
titchaten bam, do not marry amongst them and the context of the
verse is the seven Canaanite nations. So therefore it's prohibited, we'll get
later to how do you extend it beyond the seven Canaanite nations.
So that's how we know you're not allowed to marry. Ashkachna d'lo
tafsi ba kiddushin אשכחנא דלא תפסי בה קידושין Ashkachna d'lo tafsi ba
kiddushin fine so kiddushin קידושין kiddushin doesn't take effect. Vevalda kamota minalan
וולדה כמותה מנלן, Vevalda kamota minalan, how do you know that the
child is considered not Jewish? Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Amar Rabbi Yochanan
mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. So says Rabbi Yochanan in the name
of Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. De'amar kra דאמר קרא: De'amar kra: Ki
yasir et bincha me'acharai כי יסיר את בנך מאחרי. Ki yasir et
bincha me'acharai. They will
he will cause your son to stray from away from me. So
and from this we learn: Bincha haba miyisraelit karui bincha בנך הבא
מישראלית קרוי בנך, Bincha haba miyisraelit karui bincha, your child from a
Jewish woman is considered your child, ve'ein bincha haba min ha'avodat kochavim
karui bincha ela bina ואין בנך הבא מן העבודת כוכבים קרוי בנך
אלא בנה ve'ein bincha haba min ha'avodat kochavim karui bincha ela bina
but your child that you have with a non-Jewish woman is not
considered your child rather her child. Now how do you get that
from the pasuk פסוק? pasuk? Where did you see the pasuk פסוק
pasuk said about whose child it is and whether it's yours or
hers? So Rashi רש"י Rashi says there's an obvious problem with this
pasuk פסוק pasuk because the pasuk
פסוק pasuk says: Bitcha lo titein livno uvito lo tikach livnecha
בתך לא תתן לבנו ובתו לא תקח לבנך. Bitcha lo titein livno
uvito lo tikach livnecha. So don't give your daughter to their son
and don't take their daughters for your son. And then it says
because he will turn your son away from me. So it should
have either been because she the non-Jewish woman will turn your son
away from me or he the non-Jewish man will turn your daughter
away from me. What does the verse mean he will turn your
son away from me? So what's it talking about? So Rashi רש"י
Rashi says the he,
your son is not the one that has now married into the
non-Jews it's your grandson okay so the pasuk פסוק pasuk is don't
give your daughter to their sons because he your non-Jewish son-in-law will
turn your grandson away from me. So alright you got it? Now
that means but it's still your son it's still your grandson so
it must be that your daughter's son that she had with this
non-Jewish man is still Jewish and therefore we're afraid that this non-Jewish
husband right will now turn your grandson who is your grandson and
Jewish away from me. People get that? Yes? So that's how we
learn that out. That's what Rashi רש"י Rashi says. Okay Tosafot תוספות
Tosafot however disagrees and Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says
the
following. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says okay so we have
you
okay and here are the non-Jews sorry need to get through got
through
okay
so Rashi רש"י Rashi says it's because he will take your daughter
okay and then they will have a child so this will be
a son so it says yasir יסיר yasir
he will turn bincha
בנך bincha your son away from me okay because he will turn
your son so it's that he will turn your daughter away from
me he will turn your son so you see that in this
case of a Jewish mother non-Jewish father it's still your son that
is now being taken away from the faith okay I understand but
that's what the pasuk פסוק pasuk is teaching us. Okay so that's
what that's how Rashi רש"י Rashi explains how we learn out that
the son of a Jewish mother and a non-Jewish father is your
son and by the reverse presumably if it was your son and
a non-Jewish mother it would be their son it would be her
son not your son it would be not Jewish. That's how Rashi
רש"י Rashi interprets the pasuk פסוק pasuk from being he will turn
your son not he will turn your daughter. Okay Rabbeinu Tam רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam says if you just want to if you're not
confused yet Rabbeinu Tam רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says that he's bothered
by this that we're saying son here means whatever. ever, son means
grandson that hasn't been mentioned. So רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says no.
We're not talking about a child, we're not talking about any children
that this little union will have. What we're talking about is the
he means the father-in-law, the non-Jewish father-in-law. Okay, so he will turn
your son away from me. Now, what does it mean he's turning
your son away from me? So if this is your son, okay,
so it's the case where you're marrying the daughter. So he, right
it says don't don't have your sons marry their daughters because he,
now the he is somebody is the father-in-law, saying right like it's
פשט. pshat.
Yeah, I was on this one.
Okay anyway, פסוק pasuk isn't mentioning father-in-law either. Okay anyway, so he
will turn your son away from me. Now what does that teach
you about the nature of the progeny? Because what what he's saying
what it means to turn your son away from me is that
the kids are going to be not Jewish. So if the kids
are like not Jewish, that means that basically, you know, he's pulling
the whole family's sort of being pulled away from Judaism, right as
opposed so that's that's how he's sort of he's learning how that's
how he reads the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, I think רש״י's Rashi is
actually a little bit simpler. Anyway, somehow because of the grammatical problem
he will turn your son away from me we are saying that
what that teaches us is is that I'm going to read it
רש״י's Rashi way that the child of that union your grandson is
still Jewish if it's your daughter if it's your Jewish daughter and
therefore and if he's still going to be Jewish and he'll be
turned away because of his Jewish father. So that teaches you let's
go back and read that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, בנך הבא
מישראל קרוי בנך. bincha haba miyisrael karuy bincha. So your son if
it's the Jewish woman and the non-Jewish husband it's then he the
non-Jewish husband is going to turn your grandson away from me. So
the union of the non-Jewish man and the Jewish woman is still
Jewish. But the reverse would not be true. ואין בנך הבא מן
העובדת כוכבים קרוי בנך אלא בנה. ve'ein bincha haba min ha'ovedet kochavim
karuy bincha ella benah. But if it was the reverse it was
your Jewish son and their non-Jewish daughter then he would not be
turning your children away from me because they wouldn't be Jewish to
begin with because the kids of the non-Jewish mother would be not
Jewish. Okay so that is now you know you can understand like
it's not like so such a blowout proof from the פסוק pasuk
you know what I mean it just starts from a grammatical problem
he will turn your son not he will turn your daughter which
would have been a more straightforward thing to say. But this is
on which the גמרא Gemara bases the idea of matrilineal descent.
Yeah no the way I always looked at it was that and
I don't know if I'm getting the common expression correctly but you
know you know the expression daughters stay with you because who's going
to take care of the parents at the end of the day
it's going to be the daughters. So כי יסיר ki yasir means
like you know the daughter will still stay somewhat in the family
structure and
then you know and it doesn't mention son.
I understand
yes the
non-Jewish in-law
is this with a Jewish mother that we're talking about? I can't
tell it says non-Jewish.
Yeah I mean but he is non-Jewish except this forbidden union which
is what the תורה Torah is talking about. So this would be
a non-Jewish father non-Jewish mother their non-Jewish daughter yeah.
So and so that's the problem that if a Jewish son marries
this non-Jewish girl that the grandfather the father-in-law is going to take
this son away.
This son away according to רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam.
Right okay
this son away yeah that's why רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam maybe I
shouldn't have told you רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam it's easier let's go
back to רש״י Rashi okay we heard that Michael okay but we're
going back to רש״י Rashi רש״י Rashi is easier he the non-Jewish
man that your daughter is marrying will turn your sons they're going
to be your sons because which proves that they're Jewish so he
the not Jewish man that your daughter's marrying will turn your sons
away from me okay that's why רש״י Rashi is simpler. All right
that's the easier way okay now the גמרא Gemara says like this
easier to understand certainly. Okay so גמרא Gemara says like this אמר
רבינא שמע מינה amar Ravina shema mina is because
if it was the other way then then even if a woman
converted yeah then still it's a problem with the in-laws yeah yeah
but
that uh
that's true but we're assuming that the only impact power that they'll
have is based on the kids but I hear the one okay
גמרא Gemara says like this אמר רבינא שמע מינה amar Ravina shema
mina we hear from this בן בתך הבא מעובד כוכבים ben bitcha
haba mi'oved kochavim that your that the son of your daughter if
your daughter married a non-Jewish man קרוי בנך karuy bincha is still
your son. Okay now that seems to be just a complete restatement
of what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said which is why תוספות Tosafos
tries to make רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say something a little different
but it doesn't matter. He's basically re-saying the same point.
Jewish mother non-Jewish father the child is Jewish which by the way
was not stated in the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah said non-Jewish
mother the kid is not Jewish. Did not tell you Jewish mother
non-Jewish father what the kid is. Okay and that's now what the
גמרא's Gemara going to question. Okay, so let's take a look. You
could have said הכל הולך אחר הפגם. hakol holech achar hapgam. You
could have said if they don't have two Jewish parents, it's always
not Jewish, you know? The משנה Mishnah did not talk about that.
But רבינא Ravina says yes, this... רבינא Ravina says explicitly the, what
do you call it, the matrilineal descent. בן בתך הבא מן עובד
כוכבים קרוי בנך. Ben bitcha haba min oved kochavim karei bincha. Okay,
still your son if it's with your if it's your Jewish daughter
had the kid. נימא קסבר רבינא עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת
ישראל הולד ממזר. Neima kasavar Ravina oved kochavim ve'eved haba al bat
Yisrael havlad mamzer. Now the גמרא Gemara thinks ironically, oh, you're saying
it's still Jewish, that actually means it's going to be a problem,
it's going to be a ממזר. mamzer. Why is it going to
be a ממזר? mamzer? Who can remind me from a few days
ago, what is the principle of what type of a child of
what union becomes a ממזר? mamzer?
A union that's not allowed.
That not just not allowed, but that no, that קידושין kidushin isn't
binding. So the union between a Jewish woman and a non-Jewish man,
the קידושין kidushin isn't binding, so you could say Jewish or non-Jewish
as the child. But if you say Jewish, then they're a ממזר.
mamzer. That's the normal principle, right? A kid with a through a
union that is does not have קידושין תופסין kidushin tofsin that קידושין
kidushin can't be binding, the kid is a ממזר. mamzer. So if
you would say non-Jewish, which you would actually say in a way
that would be better than just convert the kid and he wouldn't
be a ממזר. mamzer. Okay, but by saying Jewish, you're now suggesting
the other possible negative consequence, which is that the kid is a
ממזר. mamzer. Okay, would that be true? So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, נהי דכשר לא הוי ממזר לא הוי. nehi de'chashar lo havei
mamzer lo havei. Nobody is saying the kid is a totally כשר.
kasher. I mean, it's true he came from a forbidden union, but
רבינא Ravina didn't say he was a ממזר mamzer either. Okay, and
as רש"י Rashi explains, the case when we say קידושין kidushin isn't
תופס tofes
is when each of the parties, the man or the woman, could
marry someone else. Right, if it's a case of, you know, if
it's a case of I don't know, of adultery, if it's a
case of incest, both the man and the woman could marry somebody
else but they can't marry each other, that's the kid is a
ממזר. mamzer. But the case of a Jewish mother and a non-Jewish
father, the non-Jewish father can't marry anyone within הלכה. halacha. I mean,
he can marry non-Jews, but he can't marry anyone within our sphere
within הלכה. halacha. So that's a different type of a category. So
we have actually, right, three possibilities of a non-Jewish father and a
Jewish mother. One is we could say I mean, one is we
could say
non-Jewish, which nobody is saying, okay, although the משנה Mishnah didn't tell
us what the story is, right? This is the matrilineal descent. The
משנה Mishnah did not tell us what the story is with a
Jewish mother and a non-Jewish father. So theoretically you could have said
non-Jewish, but רבינא Ravina says, no, Jewish. But even within Jewish, so
it parallels non-Jewish mother non-Jewish, Jewish mother Jewish. It parallels. You could
have said ממזר mamzer because the kid's not through a relationship that
the קידושין kidushin is binding, or you could say the most lenient,
which is Jewish and not ממזר. mamzer. But the גמרא Gemara still
uses this phrase not כשר. kasher. Now what type of a הלכה
halachic status is not כשר? kasher? Does it just mean yeah, it's
not good thing, there's some stigma, it's not appropriate, it came through
a forbidden union, what does exactly not כשר kasher mean? So it's
interesting, I'll just say two things about that. One is that there
are some גמרות Gemaras that understand that when they're talking about הלכות
halachos that apply to a גר, geir, they say they also sort
of think that maybe sometimes some of this should relate to a
case of a Jewish mother and a non-Jewish father because even though
that person isn't a גר, geir, right, nevertheless their Jewish identity is
somewhat you know
certainly biologically only halfway. So technically we for, you know, not technically,
הלכתית halachically we put them in the Jewish category, but there's something
like you know that's a little bit like in the sort of
quasi גר geir category, you know, because they didn't totally it's not,
you know, a גר geir is different. I mean a גר geir
started totally non-Jewish and then did an act of conversion. This person
didn't do an act of conversion, but there's some non-Jewish component there.
So that's number one, interesting in terms of how the גמרא Gemara
when the גמרא Gemara thinks about גר geir does it also somewhat
consider the case of non-Jewish father. The other place where it's very
relevant is the question and a lot of people aren't aware about
this of כהנים, kohanim, that there's a whole debate not on this
גמרא, Gemara, this גמרא Gemara gives a hint to it, but in
another גמרא Gemara in a debate how we פוסק posken about whether
a כהן kohen is allowed to marry a woman with a non-Jewish
who was born from a non-Jewish father, even with a not even
with a Jewish mother.
A woman, I'll say it again,
I said that wrong, excuse me, whether a male כהן, kohen, thank
you, whether a male כהן kohen is allowed to marry a woman
born from a Jewish mother non-Jewish father. Is this idea of not
כשר kasher somehow create some problem for a כהן? kohen? Not a
דאורייתא de'oraita problem, but some דרבנן de'rabbanan problem or whatever problem it
is. Not כשר. kasher. I mean, the גמרא Gemara doesn't spell it
out, but I'm just pointing out that, you know, it's not clear
at all that it has הלכה halachic ramifications, but two areas where
this status is dealt with is number one issues about גרים, geirim,
does it a little bit give them consider them somewhat to be,
you know, in a quasi גרים geirim category, and number two vis-a-vis
כהן. kohen. All right, but now we've got the principle: non-Jewish mother,
not Jewish, Jewish mother, Jewish. Good. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, so now גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, ניחא
קשיא
לא lo? הוי ממזר mamzer, לא lo?
הוי
*Nicha
kashya lo havei mamzer lo havei*,
I didn't read the punchline, פסול psul מקרי *pasul mikrei*. He's considered
פסול psul. *pasul*, he's not considered a ממזר mamzer? *mamzer*, he's considered
פסול psul *pasul*. So what exactly פסול *pasul* means, that's what I
just discussed, like one discussion is for a כהן kohen *Kohen*, other
discussions etc. But certainly it's obviously not ideal that he doesn't have
a Jewish father. ההוא בשבעה גוים כתיב *Hahu beshivah goyim ketiv*.
Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has another question. ההוא בשבעה גוים כתיב
*Hahu beshivah goyim ketiv*, שאר אומות מנלן *she'ar umos minalan*?
That פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of לא תתחתן בם lo titchaten bam *Lo
Tit-chaten Bam*, and which refers to the איסור issur *issur* of intermarriage
and also refers to the status of the child of such an
intermarriage, is talking about the seven Canaanite nations. How do you know
to apply this to the other non-Jews? אמר קרא amar kra, *Amar
kra*, so the verse says, כי יסיר את בנך ki yasir et
bincha. *ki yasir es bincha*, because it says, he will turn away
your son, לרבות כל המסירים *l'rabos kol hamisirim*. So the fact that
it describes the problem with this is that it'll turn away your
child, that comes to teach you that the verse is not limited
to the seven Canaanite nations. It refers to any non-Jewish nation, any
non-Jewish person who will turn your child away from being Jewish. Okay,
so that broadens the context of the verse. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, what?
I'm not understanding the connection between the two.
Okay, first the context of the פסוקים psukim *psukim*, right? I mean
if you open up, you know, if you look in the פסוקים
psukim *psukim* there in דברים *Devarim*, right? It says you're going to
go into the land and whatever, and you know, the seven Canaanite
nations, don't intermarry with them. It's explicitly the context of the seven
Canaanite nations. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says how do we know
to expand it that these statuses apply to all non-Jews? So since
the verse says that the reason you shouldn't give your son to
their daughter and your daughter to their son is that they'll turn
your child away from me, so that is explaining that tells us
if that tells us the reason we can use that reason to
determine the parameters of who are we referring to.
Since that reason applies to all non-Jewish nations, that expands for the...
now what's probably bothering you is but okay, but the verse says
seven Canaanite nations.
And maybe they're the ones who would lead your kids astray?
And maybe they're the ones that are the most dangerous. Right. So
let's look at the next line of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: הני לרבי שמעון דדרש טעמא דקרא *Hani l'Rabbi
Shimon d'daresh ta'ama dikra*. That's good for רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* is willing to use the reason of the פסוק
pasuk. *pasuk* to redefine the parameters
of the פסוקים psukim *psukim*. אלא לרבנן L'rabanan, מאי טעמא *Ella l'Rabbanan
mai ta'ama*, but for the רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan* who do not explain
the reason of the verse, what can you say? Now that does
not mean that the רבנן *Rabbanan* say, oh you're not allowed to
try to discuss what the reason of a מצוה *mitzvah* is. It
means whether you can speculate, assume it's whatever, take the reason of
a מצוה *mitzvah* and use it to redefine the parameters of the
מצוה *mitzvah* in ways in which is not the simple sense of
the verse. So the best example of this is the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* about לא lo? תחבול בגד אלמנה *lo tachvol beged almanah*, do
not take as collateral the garment of a widow. So the question
is what if she is a rich widow? Now of course for
all of us we would think, oh yeah that shouldn't be relevant
there, but we're thinking that the problem of the prohibition is because
you know, you're depriving this poor person of their garment and it's
you know oppressive etc. Won't apply to a rich person. Of course
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, who דרש טעמא דקרא *daresh ta'ama dikra*, he
also assumes it doesn't apply to a rich widow, but for a
completely different reason. He's thinking that the problem of taking the garment
of a widow as collateral is you have to return the garment
every single day, right? If you take a poor person's garment as
collateral you have to return it so that they can use it
each day and you take it at night. He says now you're
constantly dropping in this home of this widow, you know, who doesn't
have a man in the home, so it raises suspicion. That's how
he reads... so it just shows you even if you say דרש
טעמא דקרא *daresh ta'ama dikra* we can have vastly different assumptions of
what the טעמא דקרא *ta'ama dikra* is. But anyway, but he says,
so even though the verse says categorically do not take the garment
of a widow as collateral, it doesn't refer to all widows, it
only refers to poor widows. So we're willing to take what we
assume is the reason of the verse and use it to define
the parameters. Now here however,
so here the question is a little different because here the verse
gives you the reason. So the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* explains it
is the following: If the verse had not said כי יסיר את
בנך ki yasir et bincha, *ki yasir es bincha*, I would have
said yeah, the reason is he'll lead your kid astray, but that's
unique to the שבעה עממין *Shivah Amamin*, as Jenna said. They're the
ones that are the biggest threat. The verse, it was superfluous. The
verse didn't have to say כי יסיר את בנך *ki yasir es
bincha* anyway I would have assumed that because I normally am willing
to engage in the reason of the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*. If it
now tells me it tells me explicitly that, that's to tell me
that I should broaden the scope of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to
include anybody who might fall into that category.
Something like that. Okay anyway, that's the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* does
it. תוספות *Tosfos* has a slightly different version. But anyway, so for
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* we don't have to limit it to שבעה
עממין *Shivah Amamin*, we can redefine it based on כי יסיר את
בנך *ki yasir es bincha*. But according to the רבנן *Rabbanan* we
can't redefine it, so how do you know that's true? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: אמר קרא *Amar kra*, ואחרי כן תבוא אליה
ובעלתה *v'acharei ken tavo eleha u'va'alta*. Come from a completely different place,
from the case of the יפת תואר *yefas to'ar*. After she mourns
for mother and father,
then... So before this whole process, קידושין kiddushin would not be binding.
Okay? Then that's not a Canaanite nation, that's exactly about going to
war against the non-Canaanite nations outside of the land. So the גמרא
Gemara. says, אשכחן דלא תפסי בה קידושין, ashkachan delo tafsi bah kiddushin,
fine, there we know קידושין kiddushin doesn't take effect. ולדה כמותה מנלן?
v'ladah k'motah minalan? How do you know that the child is like
the mother? Because there we don't have the פסוק pasuk of כי
יסיר את בנך. So אמר קרא, כי תהיין לאיש שתי נשים וילדו
לו, ki tiheyena l'ish shtei nashim v'yaldu lo, right? If a man
has two wives and they give birth to two children. כל היכא
דקרינן כי תהיין, kol heicha d'karinan ki tiheyena, anytime we say that
when there you are married, when the marriage is binding, קרינן ביה
וילדו לו, karinan beih v'yaldu lo, that then, you know,
if you can marry this woman, again, speaking from the male perspective,
then they're your kids. וכל היכא דלא קרינן ביה כי תהיין, v'kol
heicha d'lo karinan beih ki tiheyena, and when it is a woman,
now again we have to read this as... when it is a
woman for whom no male Jew can be married to, okay? So,
and it's קידושין kiddushin is not... not just forbidden, קידושין kiddushin is
not binding for anybody, any male Jew, right? Because it's not just
any woman that קידושין kiddushin isn't binding, לא קרינן ביה וילדו לו,
lo karinan beih v'yaldu lo, then the kids are not yours and
the kids aren't Jewish. Okay, so that's how we sort of get
it out of that פסוק. pasuk? Again, we don't get the converse.
We don't get Jewish mother and not Jewish father, right, which is
what we said before. We only get the non-Jewish mother and the
Jewish father.
Okay, one minute. אי הכי שפחה נמי? i hachi shiphcha nami? So
if that's true, we should learn the הלכה halacha by a שפחה
shiphcha also, that the kids are her kids, and we don't need
the פסוק pasuk האשה וילדיה ha'ishah v'yeladeha which we had yesterday. Okay,
which told us that the kids of a servant are her kids.
Here we're saying, as long as it's a woman that no Jewish
man can marry, the kids are not yours, the kids are, you
know, belong to the mother. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אי הכי נמי, i hachi nami, you're right. אלא האשה וילדיה תהיה
לאדוניה למה לי? ela ha'ishah v'yeladeha tihiyeh l'adoneha lama li? So what
do I learn from the verse that the children go to the
mother according, you know, I already knew that in the case of
the שפחה? shiphcha? גמרא Gemara says, לכדתניא, lichdetanya, like we taught in
a ברייתא, braita, דף ס"ז עמוד א', daf samech-zayin amud aleph, האומר
לשפחתו, ha'omer l'shifchato, somebody says to his female servant, הרי את בת
חורין, harei at bat chorin, you are a free woman, ולדך עבד,
u'vladech eved, but your fetus child that's in your womb is going
to remain a slave, I am not freeing the, you know, your
unborn baby. הולד כמותה, havlad k'motah, דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי. divrei Rabi
Yossi HaGlili. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi Yossi HaGlili says he can't do
that. If you're freeing the mother, the child automatically is free no
matter what you say. וחכמים אומרים דבריו קיימין. va'chachamim omrim d'varav kayamin.
And the חכמים chachamim say no, you're able to split it. מפני
שנאמר mipnei shene'emar because it says האשה וילדיה תהיה לאדוניה, ha'ishah v'yeladeha
tihiyeh l'adoneha, the woman and the children will be to the master.
So the גמרא Gemara, says, מאי תלמודא? mai talmuda? What did you
learn from that verse? How did that verse say you can split,
you know, and free the mother and not free the kids? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא אליבא דרבי יוסי הגלילי, amar Rava
aliba d'Rabi Yossi HaGlili, that last line that quotes the verse is
supporting רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabi Yossi HaGlili who says you can't split
it. How do I know you can't split it, free the mother
and keep the kids? Because it says, האשה וילדיה תהיה לאדוניה. ha'ishah
v'yeladeha tihiyeh l'adoneha. When it's... when the mother is your slave, then
the kids are your slave. But you cannot do it so that
the mother isn't your slave and the kids, the unborn kids, are
still yours. Okay, so that's what you learn from the פסוק, pasuk
at least according to רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabi Yossi HaGlili, that you
cannot free the mother and keep the kids. But basically according to
this, we either learn the idea that there's no קידושין kiddushin and
the kids go by the mother by לא lo תתחתן בם because
לא תתן לבנך lo titein livnecha or כי יסיר את בנך, right?
Or, and we apply that to all non-Jews, or we learn it
from כי תהיין לאיש ki tiheyena l'ish וילדו לו. v'yaldu lo. Only
a woman for whom קידושין kiddushin is binding for some Jewish man
are the kids go by the... follow the father, otherwise they are
the mother's and then we assume the reverse, that a Jewish mother
and a non-Jewish father, the kids are going to be Jewish. Yes.
Amazing. If I look at the תורה, Torah, it seems, you know,
pretty much the opposite. It seems that a Jewish man who marries
a non-Jewish woman, the קידושין kiddushin. is valid and the kids are
Jewish. Because what do you do with יהודה Yehuda and יוסף? Yosef?
Yeah, look, you are totally correct that the פשט pshat of the
פסוקים is that when you're basically... look, it's משפחותם לבית אבותם. mishpachotam
l'veit avotam. It's a tribal patriarchal society. Everything follows the father. You
know, the woman would be presumed that you leave... the woman leaves
her home and goes to the husband's home, right? So, you know,
I mean, and... so of course the natural... I mean, that's the
natural thing is to assume that it would be all patrilineal, which
is why this גמרא Gemara is so shocking in the way that
it says that everything is patrilineal except when it comes to religion,
which is matrilineal. You know, so historians say that, yes, that there
was a time in Jewish history before the rabbinic period when probably
it did go by the father, you know, or maybe it went
by both, but certainly the matrilineal they see as something that sort
of came through, you know, or got crystallized in the rabbinic period,
which doesn't have to threaten us. I mean, for anybody who believes
that תורה שבעל פה Torah she'be'al peh is, you know, is a
process in which the rabbis are empowered to... Right, I mean it's
certainly the פשט pshat is
that in a patriarchal patrilineal society, why should this be any different?
And I agree with you, but yeah. Right, I mean they don't
answer any of this, I mean... I know. Yeah, Jenna. It looked
like that last little bit of גמרא Gemara left the
חכמים chakhamim with
no proof, right?
Right, I
mean they don't דורשן darshen the פסוק pasuk, the same way, you
know? But that so right, you know? So they don't have a
proof, but they don't feel that, you know, they have to read
the פסוק the way רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi reads it. Let's look
at the next משנה, Mishnah, let's wrap up this פרק. perek. רבי
טרפון אומר יכול אני לטהר את הממזרים. Rabbi Tarfon omer yakhol ani
letaher et hamamzerim. I can make ממזרים, mamzerim, not make them not
ממזרים, mamzerim, but at least get their kids to not be ממזרים.
mamzerim. How are you going to do that, since we said if
either the mother or the father is a ממזר, mamzer the kid
is a ממזר? mamzer, So he says כיצד ממזר שנשא שפחה, keitzad
mamzer shenasa shifcha, because I'm going to base it on what we
just taught in the previous משנה. Mishnah. Have the ממזר mamzer marry
a slave woman. ולד עבד. vlad eved. A non-Jewish... no, I mean,
whatever, what do you mean non-Jewish slave? I mean, it's not an
עבד עברי. eved Ivri. שפחה shifcha means a שפחה כנענית. shifcha Kanaanit.
Right. Yeah. Have him marry a non-Jewish slave woman. I mean, she's
part-way kind of
in מצוות mitzvot because, whatever, she's halakhically a שפחה. shifcha. Okay.
So anyway, have him marry a slave woman where we said that
the kids are slaves, and if they're slaves, then they follow the
mother. The whole label of ממזר, mamzer. you know, presumably only applies
to Jews, right? So once they follow the mother, presumably the ממזר
mamzer identity is irrelevant and they're non-Jews. ולד עבד. vlad eved. שחררו,
shichraro, and then free your kids. נמצא הבן בן חורין, nimtza haben
ben chorin, and then the kid will be a free Jewish non-ממזר.
mamzer So רבי אליעזר אומר הרי זה עבד ממזר. Rabbi Eliezer omer
harei zeh eved mamzer. No, I'm sorry, the ממזר mamzer, status passes
on. Now he's worse, right? So it's an interesting question that a
slave can also have a ממזר mamzer status. Okay, let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara By the way, I will tell you
that רב משה Rav Moshe has a תשובה teshuvah where he basically
suggests implementing this in practice. He says, if you have a ממזר,
mamzer, what should you do? Because even though we're going to learn
in the next משנה Mishnah that a ממזר mamzer can marry a
גיורת, giyoret, for example, or a ממזרת, mamzeret, the kids are still
going to be a ממזר, mamzer which is what we learned in
the previous משנה. Mishnah. Even if there's no, you know... so what
רב משה... Rav Moshe... oh no, the previous משנה Mishnah didn't say
that. The previous משנה Mishnah said when there's יש עבירה. yesh aveirah.
But nevertheless, that's still the הלכה, halakhah, right? The previous משנה Mishnah
only spoke about the case of... hold on... it says יש עבירה.
yesh aveirah. Anyway, but even in the case where אין עבירה, ein
aveirah, where it's a ממזר mamzer and a גיורת, giyoret, right, I
think the גמרא Gemara, even discussed that case. Yeah, גר שנשא ממזרת
יש קידושין הולד הולך אחר הפגם. ger shenasa mamzeret yesh kiddushin havlad
holech achar hapagam. Right. So anyway, it doesn't solve the משנה, Mishnah,
that was one of the exceptions the גמרא Gemara said yesterday. Fine.
Anyway, the הלכה halakhah is that there's ways in which a ממזר
mamzer, can marry, but it doesn't stop the kids from being ממזרים.
mamzerim. A ממזר mamzer, can marry ממזרת, mamzeret, or a ממזרת mamzeret
can marry a ממזר, mamzer or גר, ger, גיורת, giyoret, etc., but
the kids are still ממזרים. mamzerim. So רב משה Rav Moshe says
what you should, a person should do, if he or she... well,
if he, we'll talk about she in the גמרא, Gemara if he's
a ממזר, mamzer is go ahead and date non-Jewish women. Find a
non-Jewish woman who you want to marry, who's prepared to, who wants
to buy into the following scheme. Okay? And basically, then קונה koneh
her as an עבד, eved, live with this woman without קידושין. kiddushin,
It's the husband himself who קונה. koneh. Exactly, or exactly, because then
he's going to have to be able to free her at the
end. Okay, there has to be his... anyway, קונה koneh her as
a שפחה, shifcha, as an עבד, eved, you don't have קידושין, kiddushin.
live together, you know, your entire married life until you're done having
kids. Okay, she would still be חייב במצוות. chayav be'mitzvot. The irony
of this, or the non-irony of this, is that her חיוב מצוות
chiyuv mitzvot would be exactly the same as a Jewish woman, because
a slave's obligation in מצוות mitzvot is the same as a woman.
So actually her הלכות נדה hilkhot niddah would still apply because, you
know, a שפחה כנענית shifcha Kanaanit or עבד, eved, whatever, you know,
the same הלכות halakhos apply. So הלכות נדה hilkhot niddah applies to
a שפחה כנענית. shifcha Kanaanit. So anyway, so basically all the same,
all the normal הלכות halakhos would apply, you just halakhically wouldn't be
married, but it would be anyway. So you'd have all your kids,
and when you're done having your kids, you free the mother and
you free the kids. Okay, and that's how you solve ממזרות, mamzerut,
and then she becomes a free Jewish woman and then you can
do a קידושין. So why not just do this for conversion also?
That's what I'm saying, it could solve two problems. What, I'm saying
one more time? If there's a woman who really wants to convert
and there's a בית דין beis din who's being really difficult and
pressure-y, she could just be taken as an עבד eved by a
man and then that was all gone, I think. Yeah, what are
we even doing? Well, that gets to the question that conversion also...
that also gets to the question that conversion also requires קבלת מצוות.
kabbalat mitzvot. Now, but it might be whether the קבלת מצוות kabbalat
mitzvot can be forced in the case of a conversion or whatever,
but it's not like the בית דין beis din that is so
restrictive about conversion is all of a sudden going to say, "Oh,
okay, well שפחות, shifchos, that we're good with." Believe me, they'll find
some problem with making her into a שפחה. shifcha. What? Then you
need the בית דין, Beis Din, right? Or do you need a
בית דין Beis Din to? You need, yeah, yeah, yeah, because the
גמרא Gemara says כשם שטובלין את הגר כך טובלין את העבד keshem
shetovlin es hageir kach tovlin es ha'eved or whatever, yeah. There's like
all these הלכות halakhos of how you make somebody into an עבד.
eved. Okay, anyway, so it just wouldn't be- these children would be
his children. Oh, that's true. Legally they would not be his children.
I mean, you know, it would sort of be like an adoption
case essentially, right? הלכתית, halakhically, because once- as slaves they're not his
kids and as freed children they're not his kids. They wouldn't inherit
him. They wouldn't- yeah, exactly. In an adoption also they הלכתית halakhically
not their children. Correct. Okay. And they're not strictly חייב במצוות, chayav
bemitzvos, the kids, are they? Yes they are. Once they're freed they
are. Yeah, but until then. Well it depends- yeah, until then, correct.
They're not- well, they have the same level of חיוב chiyuv as
women. But they're men. But these male children.
So whatever obligation- I
mean it's interesting, how does חינוך chinuch work in- under age עבדים?
avadim? I
have no idea how to answer that question. What? Can't you just
free them once they're born? Do they have to wait until? That's
true,
that's true. I think you're right. He could free the kids as
they're being born. He doesn't have to wait. He just can't free
his wife until he's done having kids. Yeah, you're right. You're right.
You could free the kids as they're being born. Okay fine. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, they raise
a- a question. רבי טרפון- איבעיא להו, Rabbi Tarfon- ibaia lehu, or
the question was raised: רבי טרפון לכתחילה קאמר, Rabbi Tarfon l'chatchila ka'amar,
when רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says here's how you could solve the
ממזר mamzer problem, does he say it's מותר muttar or דיעבד קאמר,
di'eved ka'amar, only בדיעבד? b'di'eved? The question being is a ממזר לכתחילה
mamzer l'chatchila allowed to marry a שפחה? shifcha? A ממזר mamzer, is
allowed to marry a גיורת, giyores, but is he allowed to- because
there's no איסור issur for ישראל Yisrael to marry a גיורת. giyores.
But there's an איסור for ישראל Yisrael to marry a שפחה. shifcha.
Is a ממזר mamzer. allowed to marry a שפחה? shifcha? That's the
question. So the גמרא Gemara says תא שמע, ta shema, come and
hear. אמרו לו לרבי טרפון, Amru lo l'Rabbi Tarfon, they said to
רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, טיהרת את הזכרים, tiharta es hazacharim, that works
for the males, the male ממזר, mamzer. ולא טיהרת את הנקבות, v'lo
tiharta es hanekevos, not the females. Okay, what does that teach you?
אי אמרת לכתחילה קאמר, Ei amart l'chatchila ka'amar, the גמרא Gemara says
what's the difference between males and females? If you're allowed to go
ahead and in public say, "Hey, you know, I'm looking for a
שפחה shifcha to marry," so ממזרת נמי תנשא לעבד, mamzeres nami tinasei
l'eved, so let her also marry an עבד. eved. So the גמרא,
Gemara bizarrely- not ironically- and bizarrely thinks that the difference between the
male and the females is the following: if you're not לכתחילה l'chatchila
allowed to marry a שפחה shifcha or an עבד, eved, so a
man can go somewhere anonymously, pretend that he's an עבד eved and
look for a שפחה shifcha to marry and he could get away
with it. But a woman, you know, cannot go off anonymously somewhere
and pretend that she's a שפחה. shifcha. רש"י Rashi says there are
too many people that are, you know, fathers, brothers or whatever, who
are going to protect their, you know, their daughter, sister and so
on, and she's not- she doesn't have the same freedom as a
man to go off on her own somewhere and pretend she's somebody
that she isn't. Okay, so that's the way רש"י Rashi understands it.
So if you had to fake it and pretend you were an
עבד eved to get them to in order to marry a שפחה,
shifcha, well that a man could do, a woman couldn't do. That...
but if it's לכתחילה l'chatchila you're allowed to do it, why couldn't
a woman do it? So the גמרא Gemara says- so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, "No, עבד אין לו חייס." eved ein lo
chiyus. So it says a lot of things in those four words,
but it basically says this doesn't work for slaves, right? For male...
men. What- you don't even understand the question. A non-Jewish man, Jewish
mother, what did we just say the kid was? Jewish. Right? Non-Jewish
man, Jewish mother. So Jewish mother who's a ממזרת mamzeret and a
slave, what would you say the kid is? A Jewish ממזר. mamzer,
Right? So that's what they said. It doesn't go by the father.
If the father is a slave, then the kid doesn't become a
non-Jew. The kid would follow the mother and it would be a
ממזר. mamzer. It only works if the father is the ממזר, mamzer.
and then the kid follows the mother and the mother's not Jewish.
It's so funny what the גמרא'ס הוה אמינא Gemara's hava amina was,
but once we established the kid goes after the mother when it's
a Jew, non-Jew issue, of course if the mother is a ממזרת,
mamzeret, the kid is going to be Jewish and therefore a ממזר.
mamzer. So this whole solution only works for a male ממזר. mamzer.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, תא שמע, ta shema,
דאושפיזכניה d'ushpizchanei דרבי שמלאי, de-Rabbi Simlai, the host, or wherever he was
lodging, you know, of רבי שמלאי, Rabbi Simlai, ממזר הוה, mamzer hava,
was a ממזר. mamzer ואמר ליה, v'amar lei, רבי שמלאי Rabbi Simlai
said to him, "אי אקדמתך, ei akdamtach, if I had, like, known
you earlier, טיהרתינהו לבניך, tihartinhu l'vanecha, I could have made your kids
not ממזרים." mamzerim. Meaning if I had known you before you got
married, I could have advised you who to marry and you made
your kids not ממזר. mamzer So the גמרא Gemara says אי אמרת
בשלמא לכתחילה שפיר, ei amart bishlama l'chatchila shapir, if you say לכתחילה
l'chatchila you're allowed to do this, good, then he would have advised
him to marry a שפחה shifcha and that would have been מותר.
muttar. אלא אי אמרת דיעבד, ela ei amart di'eved, but if it's
you're not allowed to marry a שפחה shifcha but בדיעבד b'di'eved this
works, מאי ניהו דמנסיב ליה עצה? mai nihu d'manasiv lei eitza? What,
you know, what are we talking about? How could he go ahead
and tell him to do something that's forbidden? So the גמרא Gemara
said- no, here's how he would have made it permissible for him
to marry a שפחה. shifcha. דמנסיב ליה עצה, d'manasiv lei eitza, he
would have advised him... זיל גנוב, Zil g'nov, go burgle somebody's property.
You're not allowed to burgle either. ואיזדבן בעבד עברי, Ve-izdabein be-eved ivri,
then you'll be sold as an עבד, eved, and once you're sold
as an עבד עברי, eved ivri, an עבד עברי eved ivri is
allowed to marry a שפחה כנענית. shifcha kena'anis. So even if it's
אסור assur for a ממזר mamzer to marry a שפחה כנענית, shifcha
kena'anis, it would have been מותר muttar for an עבד עברי. eved
ivri. So the גמרא Gemara obviously says, now רש״י Rashi says isn't
it אסור assur to steal? So it says alright, the גמרא Gemara
could ask that. But anyway it rejects this suggestion for another reason.
The גמרא Gemara. says like this. The גמרא Gemara says ובשני דרבי
סימלאי עבד עברי מי הוי? Uv'shnei de'Rabbi Simlai eved ivri mi havai?
Wait a minute, since when did the הלכות hilchos of עבד עברי
eved ivri apply in the days of רבי סימלאי? Rabbi Simlai? דאמר
מר, De'amar mar, אין עבד עברי נוהג אלא בזמן שהיובל נוהג. Ein
eved ivri noheig ela bizman she'hayovel noheig. It only applies when there
is a יובל. yovel. So the laws of a שפחה כנענית shifcha
kena'anis apply even nowadays, but עבד עברי eved ivri only applies when
there is a יובל. yovel. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא שמע
מינה רבי טרפון לכתחילה קאמר. Ela shma mina Rabbi Tarfon l'chatchila ka'amar.
Since we see that רבי סימלאי Rabbi Simlai was prepared to advise
somebody about this, we see לכתחילה l'chatchila that there's no prohibition for
a ממזר mamzer to marry a שפחה, shifcha, the same way a
ממזר mamzer can marry a ממזרת, mamzeres, a ממזר mamzer can marry
a שפחה. shifcha. שמע מינה, Shma mina, that's a good proof. So
the law's מותר לכתחילה. muttar l'chatchila. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה
כרבי טרפון. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha k'Rabbi Tarfon. So there
you go, it's מותר לכתחילה. muttar l'chatchila. We פסקן pasken that way.
Here it solves the problem and as was rightly pointed out, you
could, the kids could be Jewish right away as soon as they're
born they could be freed. So this is a way with a
male ממזר mamzer, to solve the problem. Okay, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
you just have to get the woman to agree. רבי אלעזר אומר
הרי זה עבד ממזר. Rabbi Elazar omer harei zeh eved mamzer. No,
the ממזר mamzer, status passes on to the kid. אמר רבי אלעזר
מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר? Amar Rabbi Elazar mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer? What's
the reasoning of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? דאמר קרא לא. De'amar kra
lo. It says ויולדו לו, Vayoldu lo, wait is that the פסוק?
What's the לא? Hold on. I think it's ויולדו לו בנים, Vayoldu
lo banim, right? Oh no no, I'm sorry. לא יבא לו. Lo
yavo lo. What's that? No no. גם דור עשירי. Gam dor asiri.
No no, I'm sorry, it's by the ממזר, mamzer, not ויולדו לו
בנים, Vayoldu lo banim, I thought about yesterday. By the ממזר, mamzer,
גם דור עשירי לא יבא להם בקהל השם. Gam dor asiri lo
yavo lahem bikhal Hashem. Even the tenth generation of a ממזר, mamzer
he, the child, whatever, cannot go. Whoever that further generation is, even
the tenth generation, that child, that person in that later generation, לא
יבא לו בקהל השם. lo yavo lo bikhal Hashem. Did I not
say the לא? The second לא? לא יבא לו בקהל השם. Lo
yavo lo bikhal Hashem. So לו lo means הלך אחר פסולה halach
achar psula that the stigma always follows him. Okay, so any future
generation will follow the father. If the father is a ממזר, mamzer,
all future generations and that means like regardless, even if it's through
union with a שפחה. shifcha. So the גמרא Gemara says הלכה כרבנן,
Halacha k'rabanan, הוא בישראל שנעשה ממזרת. Hu b'Yisrael shena'asa mamzeres. No, that's
talking about a ישראל Yisrael who married a ממזרת. mamzeres. That's when...
now what does it tell you? It's telling you not that this
פסול of ממזר mamzer? passes on, that we know, but it's telling
you a different הלכה, halacha, that even though the kid is a
ממזר, mamzer he still is his father's child. So it actually tells
you something like more positive, okay? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka datach amina,
I would have thought למשפחותם לבית אבותם כתיב, l'mishpechosam l'veis avosam ksiv,
so that it says that you go by, I'm sorry I misstated
it, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, let's do that again. Okay, let's do
this again from the beginning. Sorry. אמר רבי אלעזר מאי טעמא דרבי
אליעזר? Amar Rabbi Elazar mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer? What's the reason of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says even with a שפחה shifcha the
child is a ממזר? mamzer דאמר קרא לא. De'amar kra lo. לא
יבא לו בקהל השם. Lo yavo lo bikhal Hashem. So he, the
future generations, cannot come. הלך אחר פסולו. Halach achar psulo. Any future
generations of this ממזר mamzer are also ממזר mamzer, regardless of who
the mother is. לרבנן, הוא בישראל שנעשה ממזרת. hu b'Yisrael shena'asa mamzeres.
That is a case of a ישראל Yisrael that married a ממזרת,
mamzeres, not a ממזר mamzer who married a שפחה. shifcha. A ישראל
Yisrael married a ממזרת, mamzeres, and I might have thought that that
kid actually is not a ממזר, mamzer. that you don't follow the
פסול. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka datach amina, למשפחותם לבית אבותם כתיב, l'mishpechosam
l'veis avosam ksiv, that we are a patriarchal tribal society and therefore
the פסול does not go by the mother. And in the case
of a ממזרת mamzeres mother and a non-ממזר mamzer father, the kid
wouldn't be a ממזר. mamzer. That would be nice. אתא לו אפקיה
Ata lo afkei and לא says no, that it is going to
be that לא יבא לו, lo yavo lo, that this later child
also cannot you know is also a ממזר mamzer even if the
father was not a ממזר. mamzer? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says...
ממזר mamzer. status goes based on the father or the mother is
a ממזר? mamzer Yes. Yes. So okay, so... ישראל שנעשה ממזרת. Yisrael
shena'asa mamzeres. I would have thought you go by the father okay
and then it says no that all future generations are still a
ממזר. mamzer Well you're saying the פסוק says לא יבא ממזר בקהל
השם Lo yavo mamzer bikhal Hashem versus לא יבא לו? Lo yavo
lo? Well that's a good point. Okay, לרבי אליעזר לאו אף על
גב דכתיב למשפחותם לבית אבותם אתא לו אפקיה. L'Rabbi Eliezer lav af
al gav d'chsiv l'mishpechosam l'veis avosam ata lo afkei. הכא נמי אף
על גב דכתיב האישה וילדיה תהיה לאדוניה אתא לו אפקיה. Hacha nami
af al gav d'chsiv ha'isha v'yeladeha tihiyeh l'adoneha ata lo afkei. So
the גמרא says one minute but according to... hold on I gotta
reread this. Made sense when I did it last night. Yeah. All
right. So he's saying like this: you said that the word לו
lo is coming to tell you: don't follow the normal types of,
like you know, groupings. Normally you would assume the child goes by
the father. But when it says by a ממזר mamzer. לא יבוא
ממזר בקהל ה׳ גם דור עשירי, lo yavo mamzer bikhal Hashem gam
dor asiri, it means like regardless of how you would normally categorize
this person, a descendant of a ממזר mamzer, is a ממזר. mamzer.
That's how you're reading it. So even if the father isn't a
ממזר, mamzer the kid is still going to be a ממזר. mamzer,
We don't go by just like follow, you know, the tribal father
identity. So if that's what you're going to say, so say the
same thing if the mother is a שפחה. shifcha. So רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer says back אף על גב דכתיב למשפחותם לבית אבותם, af
al gav dechtiv lemishpachotam leveit avotam, even though we normally follow the
father's identity, עשה לו אפקי asa lo afkei the לו lo tells
you that the child is going to be a ממזר mamzer. and
we're not going to just go by the father. So הכא נמי
אף על גב דכתיב וישבע לידו את יד אדוניו, hacha nami af
al gav dechtiv vayishava leyado et yad adonav, even though normally the
child of a שפחה shifcha is an עבד eved and doesn't follow
the father, עשה לו אפקי asa lo afkei the לו lo should
tell you that no, if the father was a ממזר, mamzer. the
kid is a ממזר. mamzer Even in this case, לו lo is
just telling you it's always going to be a problem with the
ממזר. mamzer You can't get out of it, you can't go by
the normal groupings. רבנן and the Rabbis would say no: כל ולד
שבמי שפחה כנענית כולד במי בהמה דמי. kol vlad shebimei shifcha kena'anit
kevlad bimei behema dami. So we had to end with this, which
we had yesterday too. But this comparison of a slave to an
animal, but we'll just make it a little more abstract and say
that the, you know, the child of a non-Jewish woman is also
completely out of, you know, these sort of the category of in
terms of the Jewish identity, that it completely breaks any relationship with
the parent. Okay, so therefore... yeah, exactly, exactly. So basically the child
of a non-Jewish woman, the identity completely breaks from the father. It's
not just a question that the kid is Jewish but doesn't follow
the father, follows the mother. There we could say that even though
tribally שבט shevet follows the father, it still has the status of
ממזר mamzer, of the mother. That makes more sense within our normal
parameters that we're still working within Jewish identity and the question is
just does the ממזר mamzer, status pass on. Then we could say
even if it's only the mother. But in this case where the
mother is not Jewish, it's been completely outside of the Jewish identity
and therefore that would be a full break. Yes. Okay. So הדרן
עלך האומר. hadran alach ha'omer. That is the end of a very
fun and extremely important פרק perek which started with more issues about
I think תנאים tna'im and so on, if I remember correctly, but
ended with all of these issues about what types of marriages are
permissible and what the consequence of the child, is the child a
ממזר, mamzer. is the child a Jew or non-Jew or and so
on. The next פרק perek begins with a similar... continues this discussion
of יוחסין yuchsin and עשרה יוחסין. asara yuchsin. And we will see,
it's a very interesting... it has a lot of אגדתא aggadata but
a lot of very also relevant issues in terms of these הלכות
halachot of marriage and permissible marriage and issues of... what's the word
for יוחסין? yuchsin? Lineage. Lineage, I guess. Thank you. Okay. עשרה יוחסין
עלו מבבל. asara yuchsin alu mibavel. You see I was doing this,
I was doing the Y here, right? עשרה יוחסין עלו מבבל. asara
yuchsin alu mibavel. Ten different types of lineage categories, I guess we'll
call it that, came from בבל Bavel with עזרא, Ezra, they made
עליה. aliya. כהני לויא ישראלי. kohanei leviyei yisraeli. It's funny that it
has the י yud and not the ם mem ending, but it's
an adjective, I guess. Anyway, כהנים לויים ישראלים, kohanim leviyim yisraelim, חללים,
challalim, which is a כהן kohen, who's born of a forbidden union
of a כהן, Kohen let's say a גרושה, gerusha, the kid is
a חלל, challal, doesn't have קדושת כהונה. kedushas kehuna. Okay, גירי, geirei,
גרים, geirim, חרורי, charurei, which is משוחררים, meshuchararim, עבדים avadim slaves that
have been freed. ממזירי, mamzeirei, ממזרים. mamzeirim. And those are not ישראלים
Yisraelim technically? Well, they're at a slightly different status. They have different
הלכות. halachot. Yeah, yeah, yeah. All of these are ישראלים. Yisraelim. They
just have different statuses. נתיני. nesini. Okay, which is the נתינים, nesinim,
the גבעונים Givonim that, you know, basically converted under false pretenses and
the גמרא says that דוד המלך David HaMelech basically made a גזירה
gezera that they should not intermarry within the Jewish nation. שתוקי ואסופי.
shtuki va'asufi. And the שתוקי shtuki and אסופי asufi are two people
who don't know who their parents are. We'll see in a minute.
One means... well we'll see what the משנה mishna will tell you
what they mean. Right, I know. Well the משנה mishna will tell
you what they mean. Now, כהני לויא וישראלי. kohanei leviyei va'yisraeli. Now
what does it say here? Here's a nice way of seeing this.
And I'm going to do, rather than do it horizontally I'll do
it vertically because this is obviously a hierarchy. כהני לויא ישראלי. kohanei
leviyei yisraeli. Okay, let's do the list. Read it to me. חללי,
challali, גירי, geirei, חרורי, charurei, ממזירי, mamzeirei, נתיני, nesini, שתוקי, shtuki, and
אסופי. asufi. So, okay. כהני לויא וישראלי מותרים לבוא זה בזה. kohanei
leviyei va'yisraeli mutarin lavo ze baze. Okay, this group can all marry
within one... you know, everybody, anybody from this group can marry anybody
else from that group. לוי ישראלי חללי גירי וחרורי מותרים לבוא זה
בזה. levi yisraeli challali geirei vecharurei mutarin lavo ze baze. לוי ישראלי
חללי גירי חרורי. levi yisraeli challali geirei charurei. Okay. Okay, all of
these are Jews that you can intermarry with. עבד משוחרר Eved Meshuchrar
is a Jew. גר, Ger, a חלל chalal just doesn't have כהונה,
Kehuna, but a כהן Kohen, cannot marry a חלל, chalal, right, a
חללה, chalalah, right? A כהן, right, אשה גרושה וחללה isha grusha ve-chalalah
cannot marry a גר, ger, that we halachically גר ger and and
עבד משוחרר eved meshuchrar get put into those like a גר, ger,
get put into the זונה zona category because of a presumption that
they would have have had a have have have a sexual life
outside of marriage and so on. I mean, we could talk about
that later. But anyway, but all of these people are totally מותר
muttar for ישראלים, Yisraelim, but just this section is אסור assur for
כהנים. Kohanim. Okay. גיורי וחירורי עם ממזר ונתיני שתוקי ואסופי כולם מותרים
לבוא זה בזה. Geyri ve-Cheruri im Mamzer ve-Netini Shtuki ve-Asufi kulam mutarin
lavo zeh bazeh. Now, okay, now, let's, ממזר, mamzer okay, נתיני netini
that was part of דוד המלך's David Hamelech גזרה gzera but we'll
sort of assume sort of like a ממזר. mamzer. Anyway, ממזר mamzer
obviously a ישראל Yisrael can't marry a ממזר. mamzer Okay. But it
says, now this is, I always find this so difficult because the
פסוק by ממזר mamzer says, לא יבוא לו בקהל השם. lo yavo
lo bikhal Hashem. So somehow that is seen as excluding, not including
גרים gerim and משוחררים meshuchrarim because even though now they're Jewish, somehow
because they're not Jewish by birth, it's not seen as the same
sort of inner circle of קהל השם, Kehal Hashem, which is disturbing
how whatever that on the one hand the פסוקים speak about, right,
משפט אחד יהיה לכם כגר כאזרח הארץ, mishpat echad yihyeh lachem kager
kaezrach ha'aretz, and then there are areas in which they're seen as,
okay this actually gives you latitude and freedom, I understand, but there
are also negative consequences, like a גר ger can't have a position
of authority and other types of things that it's not seen as
the primary קהל השם. Kehal Hashem. Okay, that's something to be discussed
at a more theological or religious level. But anyway, so therefore a
גר ger and a משוחרר, meshuchrar, which are basically like a גר,
ger, right, started non-Jew now Jew, can marry ממזר mamzer. נתיני. netini.
Now how about שתוקי ואסופי? shtuki ve-asufi? Let's take a look at
who שתוקי ואסופי shtuki ve-asufi is. Okay, ואלו הם שתוקי הוא שהוא
מכיר את אמו ואינו מכיר את אביו. ve-eilu hem shtuki, hu shehu
makkir et imo ve-eino makkir et aviv. He knows who his mother
is, he doesn't know his father. So he says, Mom, where's Dad?
And Mom says, oh, just be quiet, shut up, שתק, shtak, שתוקי.
shtuki. Okay, so or רש"י says maybe he calls somebody else Daddy
and his mother says shh that's not your father. Okay, anyway, the
guy whose mother's currently married to. Anyway, that's so you don't know
the father. אסופי asufi is כל שנסף מן השוק. kol sheneesaf min
hashuk. It's an orphan, a foundling, exactly, gathered in from the market,
left in the basket. ואינו מכיר לא את אביו ולא את אמו.
ve-eino makkir lo et aviv velo et imo. So basically those two
are considered to be ספק ממזרים. safek mamzerim. Now I do have
to say, the fact that a שתוקי shtuki is a ספק ממזר
safek mamzer is pretty funny because if the mother doesn't, if we
don't know who the father is, but the mother was an unmarried
woman, right, so the only, I mean it's not a question of
did she commit adultery, the only question is like what, was it
his her brother? I mean how can you have a kid that's
a ממזר mamzer. if it's not a case of adultery? It would
have to be basically what? If the father was a ממזר. mamzer
Oh, you're so right. That's such a good point. Okay, thank you.
I don't know why I was like one minute, that would have
to be an incest case but you're telling me right of course
if the father was a ממזר. mamzer, Excellent. Okay, forget what I
just said. That's absolutely correct. Okay, good. So if you don't know
who the father is, or you don't know either parent is, no
but it might be, right, חשש choshesh for incest would be bizarre.
But if you have no idea who the father is, it's true
it's probably still a מיעוט, mi'ut, but it's not as that we
wouldn't anyway. Okay, well we'll see, but יוחסין yuchsin in general, it's
a good question. יוחסין yuchsin in general, we don't just go by
like we're more מדקדק medakdeik than just going by like רוב. rov.
It's sort of like, take this analogy for what it's worth. Before
the הכשר hechsher industries came onto the scene, you would basically say
yeah, whatever, what's the חשש chshash here, even if it's very unlikely
there's something there's something טרף treif even so it would be בטל,
battel, we have the ראשונים Rishonim deal with like they talk about
how you could go buy non-Jewish bread and they say yeah, because
it probably we can assume that the eggs didn't have kosher eggs
and didn't have blood spots and we can assume they didn't do
this and we can assume they didn't do that, fine go ahead
and buy the bread. Okay, so that's what you have if you
don't have a הכשר hechsher industry, right? All of a sudden you
have a הכשר hechsher industry and it's like forget any הלכות halachos
of ביטול, bittul, forget anything, you can never trust anything unless you
know exactly 100 percent what's in there, even if there's a if
there's a trace a חשש chshash of some trace thing even if
a 100 percent it's בטל battel we won't give a הכשר hechsher
to it I won't eat it. That's sort of like what happened
with יוחסין, yuchsin, okay? So we're not just going to go by,
oh, probably it's not a problem. Everybody becomes super מקפיד makpid at
really knowing lineage, knowing all the details, and any time there's a
ספק. safek. Okay, so but it's not that easy because it's not
just a חומרא chumra as we're about to see. So these two
are considered ספק ממזרים. safek mamzerim. And the הלכה halacha is, so
a ישראל Yisrael can't marry or a חלל, chalal, whatever's also ישראל,
Yisrael, can't marry ממזר mamzer, or ספק ממזר, safek mamzer, which is
interesting because normally we actually say ממזר ודאי אמר רחמנא ולא ממזר
ספק. mamzer vaday amar rachmana velo mamzer safek. So maybe halachically they
can, but at least rabbinically whatever we'll see about that they're not.
But here's the But here's an even bigger surprise: a ספק ממזר
safek mamzer can marry a ממזר, mamzer. because you don't say a
ספק ממזר safek mamzer can't marry anybody. Can't marry ישראל, Yisroel, can't
marry ממזר, mamzer they'd be totally stuck. Okay, so actually this works
out as a קולא. kula. The fact that we're considering them ספק
ממזרים safek mamzerim works out as a קולא kula that allows them,
meaning if they wouldn't, they'd be allowed to marry ישראל, Yisroel, but
the point is we're willing, but we're willing to apply that status
and even allow them to marry ממזר. mamzer Doesn't that say then
they can only just marry each other? Yeah, well even each other
wouldn't work because one might be a ממזר mamzer... and one wouldn't.
It's not like they're all the same category. Okay, and again, the
same a ממזר mamzer, can marry a גר, ger, a ספק ממזר
safek mamzer can marry a גר ger as well. Okay. Alright, do
you have a question here? No? I was just trying to figure
out why a ספק ממזר safek mamzer would be below a ודאי
ממזר vaddi mamzer on the... Oh, I see. Yeah, you're right. I'm
not sure, I mean, I said it was a hierarchy, but I'm
not sure if within any particular group it's a hierarchy, you know
what I mean? So... Right, they might not be Jewish. Right, if
you're talking about the person found in the שוק, shuk, I'm wondering
if... If you don't know who your mother is, you're right, then
you might not be Jewish, that's true too. That's good too, but
then why could a ממזר... mamzer. oh, that's what we'll have to
see about that, that's a good point. Okay. Maybe in a Jewish
town? I don't know, okay, we'll see. All excellent questions. עשרה יוחסין
עלו מבבל. Asara yuchasin alu mi'Bavel. Oh, I'm sorry, אבא שאול היה
קורא לשתוקי בדוקי. Abba Shaul haya korei l'shtuki beduki. I'm sorry, right.
Thank you. אבא שאול היה קורא לשתוקי בדוקי. Abba Shaul haya korei
l'shtuki beduki. To the שתוקי shtuki he would say, no, no, don't
say shush, say let's investigate. Okay, we'll have to see what that
means in the גמרא. עשרה יוחסין עלו מבבל. Asara yuchasin alu mi'Bavel.
Oh, and here I thought we were going to catch up today.
It's all my fault, I start... I doubled back. מאי איריא דתני
עלו מבבל? Mai irya d'tani alu mi'Bavel? They went up from בבל.
Bavel. נסני הלכו להו? Nisni halchu lehu? That they went? What do
you mean they made they went up? מילתא גבייתא קמשמע לן. Milta
gavita kamashma lan. What do you mean? Never heard of the idea
of עליה? aliyah? כדתניא, Ked'tanya, וקמת ועלית אל המקום אשר יבחר ה'
אלוהיך. V'kamta v'alita el hamakom asher yivchar Hashem Elokecha. You shall go
rise up to the place, you know, go up to the place
where God has chosen. מלמד שבית המקדש גבוה מכל ארץ ישראל. Melamed
she'Beis HaMikdash gavoah mikol Eretz Yisroel. It's the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
is higher, וארץ ישראל גבוה מכל הארצות. v'Eretz Yisroel gavoah mikol ha'aratzos.
And ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel is higher than all other lands. Now
רש"י some places seems to think that he... this is meant literally
and geographically or not geographically, topographically, but clearly it means religiously anyway,
as well, at least as well, but presumably only. בשלמא בית המקדש
גבוה מכל ארץ ישראל היינו דכתיב. Bishlama Beis HaMikdash gavoah mikol Eretz
Yisroel hainu dechtiv. That's what it says, you'll go up to the
place, you're in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel and you go up to
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. דברי ריבות בשעריך, Divrei rivos b'she'arecha, there's
a fight in your cities, in your gates, וקמת ועלית. v'kamta v'alita.
So you're in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel in your city and you
go up to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. אלא ארץ ישראל גבוה
מכל הארצות מנלן? Ella Eretz Yisroel gavoah mikol ha'aratzos minalan? Where do
you know that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel is higher than all other
lands? דכתיב, Dechtiv, לכן הנה ימים באים נאם ה' ולא יאמר עוד
חי ה' אשר העלה את בני ישראל מארץ מצרים. Lachen hinei yamim
ba'im neum Hashem v'lo yomar od chai Hashem asher he'ela es benei
Yisroel me'eretz Mitzrayim. You will not say praise God that by the
life of God who brought בני ישראל Bnei Yisroel up from the
land of Egypt. כי אם חי ה' אשר העלה ואשר הביא את
זרע בית ישראל מארץ צפונה ומכל הארצות Ki im chai Hashem asher
he'ela v'asher hevi es zera beis Yisroel me'eretz tzafona u'mikol ha'aratzos and
from all the lands אשר הדחתים שם asher hidachtim sham that he
sort of dispersed them there. So you see it says אשר העלה,
asher he'ela, he is going to bring them up from all the
lands to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. So you see that ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisroel is higher than all the lands. Okay. So that's why
it says עלו. alu. Now מאי איריא דתני עלו מבבל? Mai irya
d'tani alu mi'Bavel? Fine, that's why it says עלו. alu. But why
mention that they came from בבל? Bavel? נסני עלו לארץ ישראל. Nisni
alu l'Eretz Yisroel. Right? Why mention that they came from בבל? Bavel?
מסייע ליה לרבי אלעזר. Mesayei lei l'Rebbi Elazar. דאמר רבי אלעזר לא
עלה עזרא מבבל עד שעשאה כסולת נקייה ועלה. D'amar Rebbi Elazar lo
ala Ezra mi'Bavel ad she'asa'ah k'soles n'kiyah v'ala. Now this is based
on the beginning of the ספר עזרא, Sefer Ezra, which we're going
to quote soon, it's going to... it explicitly talks about that here
are all the people that went with עזרא Ezra and it identifies
them as different families, the כהנים Kohanim families, the לויים Leviyim families,
the נתינים Nesinim families. It identifies who the families... so all this
focus on the יוחסין yuchasin is very explicit in the beginning of
the ספר עזרא Sefer Ezra of the people who came with him.
So that's what it means עשרה יוחסין, asara yuchasin, right? That means
that's that... like עזרא, Ezra, the people that עזרא Ezra came up
with, he knew their identity, he knew their category, these were the
ten different categories of Jews that came up with him. But now
what the גמרא here is saying is, is that they came up
from בבל, Bavel, which means he was helping out בבל Bavel in
the process because he saw that in בבל Bavel you have all
of these people of different genealogies, some were ישראל, Yisroel, some were
ממזר, some were this, some were that, and nobody was paying attention
to who was who and it was just going to get worse
and worse and worse. So he did a טובה tova and he
took all the people and maybe his unnecessary טובה tova because if
you read also the book, anybody who was of status and of
wealth didn't make עליה aliyah with עזרא, Ezra, they stayed where they
were in בבל. Bavel. So he took all of the sort of
lower castes or all of the people that were like less you
know had less status in society as well as there were some
כהנים Kohanim but a lot of the כהנים Kohanim were חללים chalalim
also. Anyway, and those were the ones that were willing to go
with him and in the process cleaned בבל Bavel out from all
of these problematic statuses. Okay, so he made בבל Bavel this like
sifted flour. Now בבל Bavel only had like you know the Jews...
taking them out of בבל, Bavel, not just bringing them to ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay it’s very interesting right in terms of like
you know the very humble beginnings as it were and also like
you know what it means when you’re settled and you’re comfortable in
the land and you know I mean just look at right now
you know the questions about about you know I mean ברוך השם
Baruch Hashem I mean the orthodox community we do you know we’re
not bad in terms of עליה aliyah but but you know once
you’re really doing well and prospering and comfortable it’s not always easy
to leave and to make עליה. aliyah. So the גמרא says like
this so it was the ones of the lesser status that were
willing to follow him. So let’s just finish that. The גמרא says
like this: אתמר itmar was taught. אביי אמר עלו מאליהם. Abaye amar
alu me-aleihem. No no no. עזרא Ezra didn’t force them to come
out, like they chose to go out. But as we’re going to
see, תנן, tnan, but as we’re going to see it means is
that עזרא Ezra identified them as: oh you’re the חלל, chalal, you’re
the נתין, nasin, you’re the ממזר. Once their status was identified, they
had very little choice but to oh we better go up with
עזרא Ezra because now we’re going to be rejected in this society.
So עזרא Ezra identified them and then they chose on their own
to go up. So רבא אמר העלום תנן. Rava amar he-alum tnan.
No no no he sort of schlepped them out against their will.
כתנאי בדידרבי אליעזר ketanai be-dede-Rabbi Elazar they debate over what רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Elazar said. דאמר רבי אליעזר, d'amar Rabbi Elazar, excuse me רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Elazar, לא עלה עזרא מבבל עד שעשאה כסולת נקיה ועלה.
lo ala Ezra mi-Bavel ad she-asah k'solet nekiyah ve-ala. אביי לית ליה
דרבי אליעזר, Abaye leis lei d'Rabbi Elazar, אביי Abaye doesn’t hold of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Elazar because עזרא Ezra didn’t like clean it out,
עזרא Ezra just identified them and then they acted on their own.
He was just trying to help בבל Bavel by identifying everybody’s status.
רבא אית ליה דרבי אליעזר. Rava is lei d'Rabbi Elazar. No, רבא
Rava says no עזרא’s Ezra goal was to take them out and
therefore he forced them out. אי בעית אימא iy ba’is eima if
you want to say no, דכולי עלמא אית להו דרבי אליעזר, d'kulei
alma is lehu d'Rabbi Elazar, everybody agrees עזרא’s Ezra agenda was to
take them out. The question was: how did he manage to achieve
that agenda? והכא בהא קמיפלגי: v'hacha be-ha kamifligi: מר סבר אפורשי אפרשינהו
mar savar afrushei afrashunihu that עזרא Ezra just he didn’t have to
do everything, he just identified them categorized them in בבל, Bavel, מנפשייהו
סליקו m’nafsheihu siliku and then they decided on their own that it
was in their best interest to leave. So עזרא Ezra took them
out of בבל Bavel by starting this process but not by forcing
them out. ומר סבר בעל כרחיה אסיקנהו. u-mar savar b’al korcha asikinuhu.
No he forced them out he I don’t know exactly how he
forced them but literally he forced them out. Okay let’s just read
a just read a few more lines to get to the שודא.
shuda. בשלמא למאן דאמר עלו beshalma l'man d'amar alu that they went
up on their own, היינו דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל כל הארצות
עיסה לארץ ישראל, hainei d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel kol ha-aratzot issah
l'Eretz Yisrael, all the lands are like dough. עיסה Issah is not
clean flour. עיסה Issah has other stuff in it. It’s got eggs
it’s got water it’s got whatever. So dough is in contrast to
סולת נקיה, solet nekiyah, the sifted flour. So if a land is
עיסה לארץ ישראל, issah l'Eretz Yisrael, it means ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
is seen as more refined, more identified people’s status and יחוסין yichusin
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. In other lands it’s not always known
who is who. ארץ ישראל עיסה לבבל, Eretz Yisrael issah l'Bavel, but
compared to בבל, Bavel, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is the dough because
בבל Bavel has been totally cleaned in terms of you know not
people of the more questionable status. אלא למאן ela l'man so that
makes sense. אלא למאן דאמר העלום, ela l'man d'amar he-alum, but now
why does it make sense? Everybody agrees that this is true that
these people came with עזרא. Ezra. So the question though is as
long as you know who is who, you’re also a סולת נקיה
solet nekiyah right? As long as you know exactly who’s in which
category. The idea of עיסה issah is it’s confused, it’s all mixed
together. So the question is after עזרא Ezra took these people with
him to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, did their identity and category remain
clear and well known? And if that’s true then ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael is also סולת נקיה solet nekiyah because you know there’s no
mixing, everybody is known. So if you say that it is עלו,
alu, then you understand why ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is also a
little mixed, because then they went up on their own, עזרא Ezra
didn’t control the whole process. So if they went up on their
own, maybe they didn’t want to keep their identity so well known.
עזרא Ezra identified them in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, trouble and בבל,
Bavel, trouble maker, he went back to בבל, Bavel, he went to
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and then they came in a way in
which it was not so clear what their identity was and we
can understand why ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is also not סולת נקיה.
solet nekiyah. אלא למאן דאמר העלום, ela l'man d'amar he-alum, but if
he was the one that controlled the whole process, so not only
did he identify them in בבל, Bavel, but he kept their identity
and their category known in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. מדי ידעינהו, midei
yad'inhu, everybody knew who they were. So why isn’t ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael also סולת נקיה? solet nekiyah? So the גמרא says no, מיהי
דידעי לההוא דרא, mihee de-yadi l'hahu dara, that generation everybody knew, לדרא
אחרינא לא ידעי, l'dara achrina lo yadi, but later generations it starts
getting confused again. Okay? So בבל Bavel where the people were removed
from, I mean talk about ethnic cleansing, it’s so difficult you know
talking about this, but בבל Bavel where the people were removed from,
that remains as clean flour. And ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael even though
the categories were known at the time, there's still a lot of
these other people there, so things get a little mixed up. בשלמא
למאן דאמר עלו, Bishlama le-man de-amar alu, היינו דכתיב, haynu de-chtiv, ואקבצם
אל הנהר הבא אל אחוא ונחנה שם ימים שלושה, va-ekbetzem el ha-nahar
ha-ba el Ahava va-nachane sham yamim shelosha, so this is from עזרא,
Ezra, we went to this river, we camped there for three days,
ואבינה בעם ובכהנים ומבני לוי לא מצאתי שם, va-avina ba-am u-va-kohanim u-mi-bnei
Levi lo matzati sham, and I investigated the people and there was
nobody there from בני לוי. Bnei Levi. It doesn't really mean nobody
because there's לויים Levi'im there, but it meant that לויים Levi'im were
not able to serve in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. I didn't
find anybody who was able. So that's good if it says that
they were עלו alu because then it means he didn't really pay
attention to who was there until they were traveling. Right, you understand?
It says as they were traveling, they encamped and he investigated who
he had with him. Okay, that's if they went up on their
own. אלא למאן דאמר העלום, Ela le-man de-amar ha-alum, but if he
was controlling the whole process and identifying them and bringing them out
with him, so הא מזיא זהירי, ha mazya zehiri, so he—it's clear
they know who is who. What does it mean now he paid
attention? Gemara says no, נהי דאיזהר בפסולים, nehi de-izhar bi-psulim, he had
identified who the פסולים psulim were, but what he said here is
that he saw that there were לויים Levi'im and כהנים Kohanim that
couldn't serve in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. He hadn't paid attention
to that before. Like, this list isn't about who can serve in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So this פסוק, which is during their
travels he stopped and he realized that there were כהנים Kohanim and
לויים Levi'im who couldn't serve in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that
was a new thing. We'll see, we'll get to that tomorrow. Yeah,
we'll get to that tomorrow. Okay, but that was a new thing.
But the categories were well known. Okay, so we've got this historical
reality about identifying who is who and bringing them with them to
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and tomorrow we will continue to see about,
like, look at the פסוקים in עזרא Ezra and who can marry
who.